Finding aid to the Leona C. Gabel Papers CA.MS.00150
Smith College Archives
Leona C. Gabel Papers
1848-1982
Smith College Archives
Gabel, Leona C. (Leona Christine), 1895-1980
CA.MS.00150
2.083 linear feet (5 containers)
Professor of History. Collection contains biographical material, publications, correspondence, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
Biographical / Historical
Leona Christine Gabel was born on April 15, 1895 in Syracuse, New York to Jacob and Christina Gabel. She attended Syracuse University and graduated in 1915 with majors in History and German and a minor in French. Her senior year at Syracuse she was elected into the honorary scholarship societies of Kappa Phi Sigma and Phi Beta Kappa. Following graduation, Gabel worked for two years as a teacher at Canastota High School. In 1921-22, she was the Bryn Mawr Traveling Fellow at King's College and at the Institute of Historical Research at the University of London. In 1923, Gabel joined the faculty at Smith College as an instructor. In 1928, she earned her PhD from Bryn Mawr College after writing her thesis, The Benefit of Clergy in England during the Later Middle Ages, where she analyzed the relationship between secular courts and church courts relating to the death penalty. In 1929, Gabel was named Dean of the Class of 1932 at Smith College. Gabel reached full professorship in 1940, and was named the Dwight W. Morrow Professor of History in 1961, before eventually retiring from the Smith faculty in 1963. On August 25, 1980, she passed away at the age of 85 after being hospitalized for many weeks.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes biographical materials, publications, correspondence, photographs and newspaper clippings regarding Gabel's education and career at Smith College and elsewhere.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Leona C. Gabel Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Gabel, Leona C. (Leona Christine), 1895-1980
- Index to the Collection, undated (Box 806.2, Folder 1)
- Biographical Material, 1921-1980 (Box 806.2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1918-1970 (Box 806.2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence -German-American, 1848-1914 (Box 806.2, Folder 4)
- Lecture-Alumnae College, 1938 (Box 806.2, Folder 5)
- Lecture-Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor, undated (Box 806.2, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes-Erasmus, 1959 (Box 806.2, Folder 7)
- Lecture Notes-Gilmore; Humanists and Lawyers, undated (Box 806.2, Folder 8)
- Lecture Notes-Renaissance Historiography, undated (Box 806.2, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous Material, 1965-1967 (Box 806.2, Folder 10)
- Photographs, undated (Box 806.2, Folder 11)
- Publications-Benefit of Clergy In England in the Later Middle Ages, 1930-1936 (Box 806.2, Folder 12)
- Publications-The Dialogus of Lapo di Castiglionchi: A Humanist Point of View, undated (Box 806.2, Folder 13)
- Publications-Encyclopedia Americana, undated (Box 806.2, Folder 14)
- Publications-Review of Nuntiaturberichte aus Deuschland, 1960 (Box 806.2, Folder 15)
- Retirement, undated (Box 806.2, Folder 16)
- Retirement-Correspondence, 1963 (Box 806.2, Folder 17)
- Retirement-Symposium, 1963 (Box 806.2, Folder 18)
- Retirement Symposium-Announcement Lists, undated (Box 806.2, Folder 19)
- Retirement Symposium-Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 806.2, Folder 20)
- Retirement Symposium-Correspondence-Sheehan, 1963 (Box 806.2, Folder 21)
- Retirement Symposium-Speeches, 1963 (Box 806.2, Folder 22)
- Venerable English College-"Rome", 1938 (Box 806.2, Folder 23)
- Publications-Renaissance and Reformation
  - Charles V-Holy Roman Empire-Turks; Dante, undated (Box 807, Folder 1)
  - Economic Development in the Later Middle Ages-Italian Towns, undated (Box 807, Folder 3)
  - Economic Revolution-Science-Science and Humanism, undated (Box 807, Folder 4)
  - Florence-15th and 16th century-Savonarola-15th century Italy in general, 1946 (Box 807, Folder 5)
  - Fourteenth to Fifteenth Century Plagues/Famine, 1962 (Box 807, Folder 6)
  - Fourteenth Century Towns, undated (Box 807, Folder 7)
  - Fourteenth Century War/Epidemics-"Century of Depression", 1956-1977 (Box 807, Folder 8)
  - Holy Roman Empire-14th century Church/Feudalism, 1961-1962 (Box 807, Folder 9)
  - Introduction, undated (Box 807, Folder 10)
  - Italian Renaissance Humanism, 1942-1960 (Box 807, Folder 11)
  - Map, undated (Box 807, Folder 12)
  - National Monarchies, undated (Box 807, Folder 13)
  - News Clippings, 1962 (Box 807, Folder 14)
  - The Papacy, 1960-1961 (Box 807, Folder 15)
  - Reformation Historiography, undated (Box 807, Folder 16)
  - Reformation-Luther-Calvin, undated (Box 807, Folder 17)
  - Renaissance Papacy, undated (Box 807, Folder 18)
  - Renaissance Unit Lecture, 1960-1961 (Box 807, Folder 19)
  - Venice-14th, 15th, 16th centuries, undated (Box 807, Folder 20)
- Commentaries of Pope Pius II
  - Commentaries of Pope Pius II, 1938-1961 (Box 807.1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography, 1955 (Box 807.1, Folder 2)
  - Books II, III, undated (Box 807.1, Folder 3)
  - Books VI-IX, undated (Box 807.1, Folder 4)
  - Books X-XIII, undated (Box 807.1, Folder 5)
  - Books-East Books, undated (Box 807.1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1970 (Box 807.1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence-Abridgment, 1957-1958 (Box 807.1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence-Copyright, 1958 (Box 807.1, Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, 1959 (Box 807.1, Folder 10)
  - Notes, undated (Box 807.1, Folder 11)
  - Notes to Printer, 1946-1957 (Box 807.1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 807.1, Folder 13)
  - Sales and Gift Mailing List, 1958-1959 (Box 807.1, Folder 14)
- Publications-From Slavery to the Sorbonne and Beyond: The Life and Writings of Anna J. Cooper
  - A Voice from the South, undated (Box 807.2, Folder 1)
  - A Voice from the South-Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 807.2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence-Publication-University of Chicago, 1972-1977 (Box 807.2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence-Publication-Greenwood Press, University of Massachusetts, University of N. Carolina, 1973-1979 (Box 807.2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence-Publication-Miscellaneous, 1974-1979 (Box 807.2, Folder 5)
  - Life of Anna Cooper-Manuscript-Chapter VII, 1975 (Box 807.2, Folder 6)
  - Life of Anna Cooper-Manuscript-Chapter VIII, 1975 (Box 807.2, Folder 7)
  - Life of Anna Cooper-Manuscript-Chapter IX, 1975 (Box 807.2, Folder 8)
  - Notable American Women-Anna Cooper, 1977-1980 (Box 807.2, Folder 9)
  - Notes, 1977 (Box 807.2, Folder 10)
  - Notes-Cooper-Composite Autobiography, undated (Box 807.2, Folder 11)
- Publications-From Slavery to the Sorbonne and Beyond-Source Material
  - Biographical Material, 1864-1978 (Box 807.3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 807.3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence-Annette Eaton, 1971-1977 (Box 807.3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence-Anna Cooper to Arthur Vance Churchill, 1924-1925 (Box 807.3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence-Oberlin College, Howard University, 1971-1974 (Box 807.3, Folder 5)
  - From Slavery to the Sorbonne and Beyond, 1982 (Box 807.3, Folder 6)
  - L'Attitude de la France-Introduction, undated (Box 807.3, Folder 7)
  - L'Attitude de la France-Thesis, 1925 (Box 807.3, Folder 8)
  - L'Attitude de la France-Translation, undated (Box 807.3, Folder 9)
  - L'Attitude de la France-Chapter I, undated (Box 807.3, Folder 10)
  - L'Attitude de la France-Chapter II, undated (Box 807.3, Folder 11)
  - L'Attitude de la France-Chapter III, undated (Box 807.3, Folder 12)
  - Pieces Justificatives, undated (Box 807.3, Folder 13)
  - Voice from the South, undated (Box 807.3, Folder 14)